<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, March the 24. 1624. By Barten Holyday, now archdeacon of Oxford</title>
            <author>Holyday, Barten, 1593-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839910</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4371</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1107:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, March the 24. 1624. By Barten Holyday, now archdeacon of Oxford</title>
                  <author>Holyday, Barten, 1593-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 42, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for Nathaniell Butter, and are to be sold at his shop at Saint Austines Gate in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On the occasion of the coronation of Charles I; the year date in the title is given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears a Bible verse; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant (earlier state?): lacking quire [par.] with dedication to Bishop John [Howson].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Variant; beginning to p. 7 from British Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZEKIEL 37.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>—I will make them one nation—.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED At Pauls Croſse, <hi>March the</hi> 24. 1624.</p>
            <p>BY BARTEN HOLYDAY, Archdeacon of OXFORD.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Stansby</hi> for <hi>Nathaniell Butter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at Saint <hi>Auſtines</hi> Gate in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:27"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:27"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, IOHN LORD BISHOP OF OXFORD, HIS WORTHY DIOCESAN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat which is the cauſe, for which many men doe not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh their labours, is the chiefe cauſe for which I doe publiſh mine, the danger of the attempt. I iudged this the choiſeſt proofe, whereby I might expreſſe how hardy I dare bee, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then bee vngratefull. And this courage in mee is but an effect of your goodneſſe; a goodneſſe not more acceptable for the bountie, then for the circumſtances: which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues
<pb facs="tcp:4371:28"/> as much your wiſdome, as your fauour. It is a great fauour to ſatisfie hope: but it is a skilfull fauour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it. Hope giues more ſpeedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, then poſſeſſion does; but hope giues leſſe content, then poſſeſsion giues; nay, it makes leſſe the content, which poſſeſsion giues. Which, your bounty, that well knowes how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage it ſelfe, ſo well vnderſtands, that it delights only in this noble oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, To diſturbe him, whom it bleſſes, giuing him happineſſe, ſooner then the apprehenſion of it. And yet it is a kind of mercy to giue a man the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of expectation, though of good things; the ſodainneſſe of newes, though good, being ſometimes dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But this is the only mercy, which your goodneſſe vſeth to deny: yet, for which, whiles your bountie claimes
<pb facs="tcp:4371:28"/> thankes from one, your iudgement claimes applauſe from all. And this is a part of that wiſdome, which now hath made you as eminent in the Church, as it hath hitherto made you induſtrious for the Church. Which honour, as it was begun by your wiſdome and zeale, ſo was it perfected by the wiſdome and fauour of our late Souereigne: with whoſe moſt acceptable memory, I thought good thus to conueigh my thankes. And this memoriall may bee the more gratefull, ſince it is an Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary not of his death, but of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, in the Vnion of his Britanies It was, before, my ſeruice to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; but now to his memory: then it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed my duty, but now my ſyncerity; in which only bleſsing I ſhall alwayes defend and endeuour an ambitious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Nay, this endeauour is already
<pb facs="tcp:4371:29"/> at that height, that it may almoſt make my gratitude fall into the ſuſpicion of pride, whiles it doth wiſh my meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons immortall, that ſo my thanks might be immortall. The only way of con<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e at that I haue taught my ſelfe is, not ſo much in that your bounty did helpe me, as in that your iudgment did chooſe mee; to make mee a part of your good workes: which, by their nature, muſt be a part of your ioy euen in death, and a ſigne of that ioy, which ſhall be after death. Thus is it as poſsible for you to loſe your good worke, as the neceſſarie gratitude of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips perpetually obliged, <hi>Barten Holyday.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4371:29"/>
            <p>TO ſpeake of Kingdomes may bee as full of danger, as it is of difficultie. I knew not therefore how to endeuour an apter vnion of truth and ſafety, then to ſpeake of kingdomes in the words of a King. My text was firſt deliuered by a Prophet, and hath beene ſince coyned by a King in letters of gold, a mettall not more compact, then the kingdomes he vnited. The King is the happineſſe of this day, and God the glory of it, and the day is the thankefull Hiſtorie of both. This day, in which, the expedition of the Diuine bounty did by the right of Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation preuent the act of Coronation, which graciouſly yeelds to the leiſure of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and of the ſubject; who notwithſtanding doth not make his King, but declare him; Our approbation and joy, though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they are of a naturall libertie, being yet in this politicke relation but parts of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance; which then is compleate, when we prooue our memory to be as good a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as our vnderſtanding and our will; and by the loyall Aſtronomie of an Almanacke no leſſe faithfully repreſent vnto our ſelues the reuolution of our joy; then of our time.
<pb facs="tcp:4371:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4371:3"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4371:4"/> No Coronation needs ſuch repeated ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; euery Coronation expects it; and this ſingularly deſerues it. There is in no Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an Vnion of heads: there is in euery Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation an vnion of a head and a bodie; but in this there is alſo a vnion of bodies: and then proportion as well as pietie ought to preſume an vnion of hearts. Varietie is the pleaſure of nature; but Vnitie is the buſineſſe of Nature. And therefore though the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor haue in the diuerſitie of creatures ſhewed his power: Yet hath hee as much in their v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhewed his proprietie. There is implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the creatures a Catholike ſimilitude, which is the ſecret cauſe of a poſſible vnion; &amp; ſo Diuerſity may ſeeme to ariſe, but from acceſſion of circumſtance, which being withdrawne, makes the creatures retire to their primitiue vnity. And if you would ſee this vnitie in the creatures, behold firſt the Heauens, which indeed deſerue to bee firſt beheld; and though ſome Aſtronomers haue accuſed them into a diuiſion of Spheares, yet may wee ſuſpect ſuch diuiſion to bee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Aſtronomers then in the heauens: and therefore ſome haue courteouſly preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4371:4"/> the vnitie of that great body, by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying onely the motions of the leſſer bodies, the Starres: yet diuerſitie of Spheares would not ouerthrow vnitie, but magnifie it, whileſt the inferiour Orbes doe at the ſame inſtant profeſſe a contrarietie and an obedience to the firſt moouer, ſtriuing to recompence the varietie of their bodies, by the conſent of their motions. Behold the Elements, and you ſhall find, that though they are apt to quarrell, yet as if they would ſhew the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a haſtie nature, they are reconciled with equall facility and ſpeed, and ſometimes fall ſo farre in loue with their enemies, that they ſeeme to loſe themſelues, whiles they runne halfe way to meete them. Thus doth the fire delight to be extinguiſhed into ayre, that it may ſlide neerer vnto water, as well in nature as in affection. And for a preparatiue to ſuch vnion, two oppoſite elements haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by prouidence, one friendly element interpoſed, which cunningly perſwades them to a peace by the diſcretion of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie. Behold the moſt ſullen minerals, that ſeeme to be ſetled in the ſtoiciſme of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated natures, and you ſhall find their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4371:5"/> obſtinacie ſo conquered to a change by the vnited power of Nature and Art, that they ſhall at leaſt diſſemble their diſſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and euen the fowleſt appeare as faire as the promiſes of an Alchemiſt. Or if you thinke you are not able to judge the heart of the earth, you may reade this vnitie in the face of the earth: you may reade it expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the fruits of the earth: you may ſee the ſeuerall kinds of the apple dwell vpon the ſame apple-tree, by which friendſhip of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment through their grafts, the growth and fruit is not more manifeſt, then an eaſie vnitie in their juyce. But if you would by a neere inſtruction ſee the obedience of the creatures, it diſioyned; to returne to vnitie, you may from your ſelues inſtruct your ſelues; and when mans bodie fals-off from his ſoule, in that one diſ-vnion behold two v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and nature haſtning to its firſt ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. You may ſee the body put-on an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble corruption, and be content to returne to as vnfeigned duſt, as that which is the food and curſe of the Serpent; or that into which euery beaſt muſt bee confounded; that if the aſhes of Alexander and his Bucephalus had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4371:5"/> beene put in one vrne, Ariſtotle himſelfe could not haue diſtinguiſhed them either by Philoſophy, or by flattery. You may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the eye of the ſoule ſee the ſoule at its ſeparation ſo refined by ſimilitude into ſpirit, that it is readie to miſtake it ſelfe for an angell, as if its knowledge were at the ſame time perfected and deluded. Nor will it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitate the likeneſſe, but alſo the office of an angel, and ſhal at laſt be ſent vpon a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to its owne body, which it will take vp as an angell will take vp both the body and ſoule, But becauſe the ſoule can aſcend higher by contemplation, then it can by eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, it may behold the beginning of vnitie in all things, by beholding him, who is the beginning of all things. In whom wee may ſee an vnitie in a diuiſion, and ſhew the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician a myſticall poſſibility of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding of a point, whiles wee may behold God not multiplyed, and yet diuided into perſons. Now though man be not capable of the myſterie, yet he is of the inſtruction, and may with as much caſe as delight vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that God is ſo delighted with vnitie, that it is alwayes either his nature, or his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4371:6"/> worke. It was the ſame wiſdome which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed Adam into Nations, and contracted them againe into the houſhold of an Arke. God created angels in multitude, but hee made man in vnitie; hee gaue excellence to them, but to man Supremacie: the chiefe of angels being in heauen but a ſubject; but the chiefe of men being on earth a King. And though an angell bee more like to God for purity, yet man is more like him for produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. An angell can more ſubtilly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his owne likeneſſe; but a man more powerfully can alſo partly beget his owne likeneſſe, being made a Deputie Creator; and therefore he is a King, becauſe he is a father. A kingdome by nature is but an enlarged fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and the firſt King begot his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and a father by the Romane Law had once as juſt power to execute his ſonne, as to preſerue him. The Law of God, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands our obedience to a King, commands it for him by the title of a father. Adam was by God and Nature the King of Mankind; and Nature would haue deliuered this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his firſt borne. Nor had it beene a miſtake: Nature ſaw juſt cauſe why he ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4371:6"/> haue ſucceeded, though it did not ſee a juſter cauſe, why hee ſhould not ſucceed: and though the Diuine juſtice changed the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet it changed not the Law. It did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt it, but not abrogate it; and therefore the Royalty goes ſtill with the Elderſhip. Thus he that was the firſt King, was before his people; and this agrees with the courſe of nature, by whoſe inſtruction wee know, that in the method of euery birth, which is not peruerſe, the head is elder then the body. As then both angels and man tooke their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from one God: ſo all other men tooke their beginning from one man. And God hath not onely honoured this vnity in ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but alſo preſerued it by ſucceſſion. So ſome Kings ſupply birth right by victory, and ſome by election; though to elect a King be as much newes to nature as to adopt a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and it did firſt ariſe from neceſſitie and conueniency in families, whom the bleſſing of multitude had diſpers'd and mixt. And though it were often among the Gentiles continued by faction, and by the Iewes at firſt entertayned by Fancy; yet God in the Wiſedome of his diuine indulgence did
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4371:7"/> grant their deſire, and chaſtize it; giuing them a King by choice, but it was alſo by his owne choice; he did not in the election com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend election, but Monarchie, which makes families ſo wiſe, as to become a Nation: nay, which makes Nations ſo wiſe, as to become a Nation: and by the witty happineſſe of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to prooue one to be ſtronger then two. It is as great a difficulty, as a bleſſing for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to liue in one Nation and friendſhip; but it is as great a wonder as a bleſſing, when Nations become brethren, and are diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed rather by number then affection. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham and Lot were almoſt brethren, and yet they were diuided; that they might not be diuided. Iacob and Eſau were brethren, and though one wombe could contayne them, one Countrey could not: but Iacob muſt flie, &amp; Eſau is as ready to hunt Him, as Veniſon. But Cain was at that diuiſion with Abel, that the ſame world could not hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both: and yet hee kild him for he knew not what; it was about Gods fauour, but not for it. Thus experience can hardly find vnion there, where reaſon would thinke it hard to find a diuiſion: Vnion is the happineſſe of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4371:7"/> man, and the accuſation: it being more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayned by inferiour creatures, which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſſeſſe it, then enjoy it; then it is by man, who likewiſe doth more vnderſtand it, then enjoy it. And yet it is a bleſſing not ſo excellent for the raritie, as for the increaſe: it being by nature of that thrift and cunning, that it growes in goodneſſe by growing in greatneſſe, and from number receiues excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. The vnion of families into a Citie, as it doth conquer affections vnto peace; ſo it ſelfe is conquered into a perfection by a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnion. The vnion of Cities into a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, tries the goodneſſe of a King: but the vnion of kingdomes tries his wiſdome; the ſimplicitie of juſtice beeing enough to manage one kingdome, but two will require the myſterie of wiſdome. When Nature v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites people into a kingdom, it doth but work by an humble ſafety: but when it vnites kingdomes, it workes by the tranſcendent power of loue and glory; this excellent vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being as much the delight, as the imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nature. So that although it ariſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by accident from cauſes leſſe naturall, as from pride, and force: yet the diuine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4371:8"/> hath in all ages condemned and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſuch vnion; ſtill ſuffering a great part of the world by a happy raſhneſſe to runne it ſelfe into Empires. In each of which, mee thinkes, we may obſerue ſome eminent and diſtinct bleſſing, which attends and honours the vnion of Nations. If you will wipe-off the duſt of antiquity from the Chronicles of the Aſſyrians, you may in that vnion of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſufficiently diſcerne the bleſſing of peace; witneſſe their plantations, wherein they more employed the trowell, then the ſword. Witneſſe their tower of Babylon, a worke and corruption of peace; for which, Gods accurate juſtice did ſo aptly correct them, that it made the ſame tongues, into which they were curſt, deliuer the hiſtory of the curſe. Witneſſe their City of Babylon more famous for the walles, then for the Kings; though not ſo famous for either, as for their captiues, the Iewes. The Aſſyrians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed made ſome excurſions by the ſword: but it was rather to vary their pleaſure, then diminiſh it; or vntowardly to prooue their poſſeſſion of a peace, by their abuſe of it; till at laſt they did not ſo much poſſeſſe peace as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4371:8"/> vice poſſeſt them, and now haue well neere loſt their ſtory with their Empire; which ſtood almoſt as long after the Floud, as the World from its beginning to the Floud; ſuch continuance as fairely approouing their vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as their deſtruction did condemne their abuſe of it. If you will view the Perſian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, you may in that vnion of Nations ſee, that which moſt deſire to ſee, the bleſſing of wealth; wealth enough to pleaſe and torment folly in the inuention of expence. Witneſſe their feaſts, in which they laboured no leſſe with curioſity, then with ſurfet, and by a ſtrange convulſion of gluttony, drew their ſtomacke and their palate into their eye: witneſſe their wiues, whom they adorned more then their owne ſoules, or then their gods: witneſſe their warres, wherein their wilde Xerxes brought mankind againſt the Athenians; an act, that yet might haue beene excuſed by the ſame diſproportion that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it, had hee come to conquer rather their wits, then their Countrey; witneſſe their feare, which made Darius through a deſire of peace and infamy, preſent a bribe greater then his feare, and as he hoped; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4371:9"/> then Alexander. If you will view the Grecian Monarchy (though you can hardly view it either for the luſtre, or the ſwiftneſſe) you may in that vnion of Nations ſee the bleſſing of glory; the glory of Alexander further extended then his ambition; as if hee had beene Emperour of Fame, as well as of Greece; and by this Eſſay of immortality had beene flattered after death, or recompenſed thus for the ſhortneſſe of his life; which affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him leiſure rather to deſtroy an Empire, then erect one. Yet his glory was like the Sunne's, though not his courſe; which was towards the Eaſt, and when by victory hee made the Perſians bow vnto him, he changed their obedience, but not their Religion, ſince they did ſtill worſhip the Sunne. And thus he was made a God according to his deſire; a God in this life, beyond his deſire; a God as vaine as his deſire. And ſure the world by too much beholding the glory of this Sun, hath ſtill before its eyes the dazling images of this Sunne, that now it ſcarce can ſee Greece for Alexander; who hath ſo obſcured his Country by illuſtrating of it, that it may rather boaſt of a Monarch then a Monarchy.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4371:9"/> If you will view the Monarchy of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, you may in that vnion of Nations ſee the bleſſing of ſtrength-ſtrength of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that it might haue dar'd to arme an enemy, and deride him; ſtrength of ſuch firmeneſſe, that vice could not ouercome it, but by a new way, making it grow more wanton by victory, then by peace. You may behold the degrees of their ſtrength; they threatned Parthia, frighted Aegypt, ſtrucke Germany, wounded Spaine, but deſtroyed Iudaea. You may behold the arts of their ſtrength; they conquer'd Aegypt with its owne corne, and made that their ſtorehouſe; they conquer'd Spaine with its owne gold, and made that their mine; they conquered Germany with its owne people, and made that their Campe. They could make no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of Parthia, where they receiued too many wounds: and did make none of Iudaea, where they gaue too many wounds; and all this while there came nothing from Rome, but the courage and the ſword. And thus you ſee the bleſſings which ſo conſtantly attend the vnion of Nations, that ſometimes they attend the equiuocall vnion of Nations. For
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4371:10"/> there are Nations which are vnited in cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; that murder the Chriſtian, and (which is worſe) wound his ſoule, whiles they ſlight his Chriſt, and by an arte, which the Iew ſtrangely forgot, put his Sepulchre to vſe. And yet theſe Nations enjoy by preuention, as ranke pleaſure as they ſhall be deceiued of hereafter by the forgery of their Mahomet: who was better it ſeemes at the erecting of a conſpiracy, then of a Paradiſe. Thus euery vnion of Nations is either rewarded with a benefit, or at leaſt attended with a benefit. If Nations then will deſire peace, let them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire vnion: ſo ſhall the Figge and Grape bee ripened as much by peace, as by the Sunne: ſo ſhall wee be made as ſecure by neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as by wine and innocence: ſo may we at land be as free from the ſuſpition of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as from injurie; and the Merchant in his Voyage ſhall feare but one tempeſt at a time, hauing no other enemy but the Sea. If Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will deſire wealth, let them deſire vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo may the labourer be no leſſe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his owne gaines, then of his induſtry: ſo may the Citizen haue his coffers forced open, not by the hand of the ſpoyler, but by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4371:10"/> the ſame abundance that fils them: ſo may the Countriman not need to eate his ſheepe from the Souldier, but may feed vpon them, and yet neuer hurt them; nay, grow fatter with the wooll, then with the fleſh, and make the fleece keepe the ſheepheard as warme as the ſheepe. If Nations will deſire glory, let them deſire vnion: ſo ſhall their wiſdome, which began their happineſſe, exceed it; and be extended like their dominion; and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended beyond their dominion: ſo ſhal juſtice triumph for hauing more leiſure, then occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to exerciſe it ſelfe: ſo ſhall learning helpe wiſdome and juſtice both in their practice, and in their fame by conueighing them into ſtory almoſt as immortall, as their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If Nations will deſire ſtrength, let them deſire vnion: ſo ſhall euery one bee what Cain ought to haue beene, his brothers keeper, eſteeming him no leſſe a part of his care, then of his bloud; ſo ſhall they bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſhut the gates of their Cities, which they were afraid to leaue open; leſt that, which before was counted wiſdome, ſhould now bee interpreted diſcourteſie; ſo may their Hauens expect more danger from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4371:11"/> their owne ſhelues, then from the fleet of an enemy: ſo may they preuent thoſe triuiall ſupremacies; in which the fragments of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue delighted and periſhed. Was it not this, by which Greece loſt its fame, before its liberty? Was not Athens with Sparta ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired like the Perſian? But was not Athens againſt Sparta derided like the Perſian? As then the vnion of Nations is a bleſſing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes moſt excellent for the kind; ſo doth it then become moſt excellent alſo for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, when it is betweene Nations which haue beene enemies, and when as thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies haue likewiſe beene friends; their firſt friendſhip making their diſſention admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and their diſſention making their ſecond friendſhip admirable. But becauſe example is the moſt legible character, let your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding deſcend into your ſenſe, and behold ſuch nations; behold Iudah and Iſrael, which, when they were, were not able to inſtruct themſelues; and ſince, they haue not beene, haue inſtructed the World. Behold Iudah and Iſrael; who had they ſtood vndiuided, had ſtood; and yet they were once ſo vnited, that wee can ſcarce diuide them into the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4371:11"/> names of Iudah and Iſrael; and you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to behold them, as they were vnited. You may ſee them vnited in Gods fauours; who made his other creatures pay their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to theſe creatures. Hee made the earth ſwallow vp a ſedition with the ſeditious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah from among them; hee made the waters at the Red Sea flie faſter from his people, then his people did from the Aegyptian: Hee made the moſt inexorable earth the Rocke relent into a ſtreame of waters and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto them: Hee made a tree ſweeten water for them; which was ſuch a fruit of a tree, that Paradiſe it ſelfe was vnacquainted with it: Hee made the aire feed them with meteors, compacting it into the dainty mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Manna and Quailes: Hee made the fire ſo mindfull a Guide to teach them by the ſhape and embleme of a pillar, on whom in their pilgrimage they ſhould relie, that it forgot its owne nature which would haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined it to an aſcent in a ſharper forme: He made the Sunne wait vpon their victory, and encreaſe it; by multiplying the day, as he did his fauours. You may behold them vnited in afflictions; they had made bricke together
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4371:12"/> in Aegypt, and were as hot with indignation, as their worke with the fire; being more vext with the kind of the labour, then with the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; they had beene tired together in the wilderneſſe, not ſo much with not comming to their journies end, as with not knowing when they ſhould come to it. Forty yeeres were they grieued with the diſtruſt of their owne expectation, and forty yeeres was God greiued with the diſtruſt of their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they had in the wilderneſſe for their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, beene bitten with fiery Serpents; the ſinne of their tongues being puniſhed with the teeth of the Serpents; their murmuring tongues being like fiery Serpents, by which their ſinne was chaſtiſed and expounded. Thus you ſee how God vnited them: but now you ſhall ſee how they diuided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; and as if they had remembred their owne plague onely to imitate it, they become fiery Serpents one to another. When by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of time and children they had ſpread themſelues into the breadth of a Kingdome, Gods fauour raiſes them to the height of a Kingdome, which they quickly diuide; it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4371:12"/> had not elſe beene to their minds; it had not elſe beene like their minds, which were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided. Ieroboam puts on the perſon of a King, though not the right; and by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie of Treaſon vndertakes to diſtinguiſh Iſrael from Iudah. Hee could haue vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken nothing harder, but to haue diſtinguiſhed Ieroboam from a Traitour. Yet he goes-on in his crime and cunning, confirming his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of the Kingdome by a diuiſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Had Ahitophel liued in his time, hee had certainly hang'd himſelfe for enuy of this wit; and I wonder Machiauell did not chuſe Ieroboam, rather then Caeſar Borgia for his jdoll of a Prince. What Ieroboam be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan by erecting two jdols (the number was a memoriall of the diuiſion;) Baaſha continues by the erecting of a fort; that as Ieroboam had renounced the Religion of Iudah, ſo hence-forth hee would renounce the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with Iudah. Afterward Omri to ſhew the inuention and addition of a ſucceſſour, erects a Citie againſt Iudah. Iſrael had a King before, but not a Throne; and now Samaria, as it is the younger, ſo will it alſo be counted the fairer. And it were well if the quarrell
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4371:13"/> were but in opinion; and yet it is but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. But ambition, whoſe end is alwayes but folly, doth often vſe wickedneſſe for its meanes. Wherefore Iehoaſh, who came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe in time, though neither in emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor in confidence, thinking his Samaria not perfectly vp, as long as Ieruſalem was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly vp, was vainly prouoked, and as vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſed by Amaziah King of Iudah; and with the ſpeed of the ſame fury, throwes downe the King and the wall of Ieruſalem. Yet when he had choſen his owne bribe, the ſpoile of the Treaſury and of the Temple, he returnes leauing behind him nothing but the hope of reuenge, and the God of reuenge. And when the heires of theſe injuries were repaired to ſtrength, their projects encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with their fury, they made their confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracie reach as farre as their infamy. Iſrael therefore by preuention combines with the Syrian, who was not ſtrong, yet hee was neere; Iudah combines with the Aſſyrian, whoſe fame was as good as neighbourhood, and his power better. Thus you ſee how la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably they diuide themſelues; but now will you ſee how lamentably God diuides
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4371:13"/> them? Iudahs wrath cals the Aſſyrian againſt Iſrael; and Gods juſtice brings him. Iſrael is immediatly in a bondage of feare, and Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria it ſelfe in the bondage of a ſiege. Thus were they taught to loſe their liberty, and at laſt by captiuitie to forget it; they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tranſported with their owne fury; and now by the fury of another: they were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from the pleaſure of their malice, and of their countrie. But was not Iudah too glad, and guiltie of this miſerie? And did they not as much deſerue ſuch deſtruction, as procure it? Behold the mercy and inſtruction of Gods anger: Iſrael hath now for euer ended warre with Iudah: but now is God to begin warre with Iudah. He giues them time to employ in ſorrow for their owne offence; and they peruerſely employ it in joy, for their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ruine: and were ſo vnable to foreſee their owne puniſhment, that they were not able to ſee their owne ſinne. But when their ſinne had increaſed like Gods mercie; the Aſſyrian who was now as well acquainted with the victorie, as with the way, comes to fetch Iudea into Aſſyria; depriues Ieruſalem of a King, and the King of his eyes: hauing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4371:14"/> firſt made ſight his affliction, by cauſing him to ſee the ſlaughter of his ſonnes; then making blindneſſe a double affliction, by hindring him in his captiuitie, to ſee the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of his enemie Iſrael. And as the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrian thruſt out his eyes, ſo now his captiue people may weepe out theirs: now may they ſit downe by the waters of Babylon, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them with their teares: now may they hang their Harpes vpon the willowes; their inſtruments now being as vnable to yeeld muſicke, as the willow fruit; now haue they leiſure to remember Sion, and themſelues, who did before forget both; and now may Iudah deſire to returne to Sion, though with Iſrael. But ſhall Iudah for euer bee diuided from Iſrael? Or ſhall Iudah and Iſrael be for euer diuided from their Countrie? No, they haue left it, but not loſt it; they haue not loſt their Countrie becauſe they haue not loſt their God; who raiſeth Ezekiel to raiſe their hope: and in Aſſyria they receiue their Countrie againe by promiſe, as afterward by poſſeſſion; returning from the captiuity of their bodies, to a happy captiuity of their paſſions: being now as much vnited in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4371:14"/> loue; as they were before in affliction. Iudah returnes not in ſorrow, yet in teares; wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for joy, becauſe it hath no longer cauſe to weepe, hauing now changed the place, the motiue, and the nature of its teares: through which it can ſcarce ſee Ieruſalem, which it doth long to ſee; as if they would imitate in their returne from Captiuity, the blindneſſe of their King, when hee was ledde into Captiuitie. But doth not Iſrael alſo returne, that it may repent in joy for its jdolatry and Conuerſion? Doth not Iſrael alſo returne, that it may with ſhame and delight build vp the wall of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, which with fury and delight it once pulled downe? Doth it not returne, that it may repaire the Temple, and in the Temple, with teares confeſſe how once it ſpoyled it? Doth it not returne that it may pray for Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, that it may pray with Iudah? Or is Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael now become more odious to God then captiuity is to Iſrael? is it left behind in Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, as if it were a thing as execrable, as Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria? Elſe why doe wee not ſee them in their journy, vnleſſe they be clouded in the duſt of their journy? why do we not heare the tumult
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4371:15"/> of their returne; vnleſſe their joy be ſo man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly, that it is afraid to make a noyſe? Why doe we not heare the ſhouts of liberty, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they are become hoarſe with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? Or peraduenture they are not yet on their way? Or peraduenture they will not be yet on their way: or it may be, they will returne to Iudah, but not with Iudah? Shall we then delude our ſelues into the Creed of the Iewes, beleeuing as the Doctors of their Poetrie doe at this day deliuer, that Iſrael hath changed Aſſyria for the Caſpian moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and their captiuity for a ſecond wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe? Shall wee beleeue that there they multiply children, as theſe Teachers doe their fancies, to make vp the traine and fable of a Meſſias, which theſe our Iewes haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken for them? Or to returne ſtrong to Ieruſalem, for feare of another falling-out? Or not without their Meſſias, as if hee were to make their peace with Iudah, as well as with God? Shall wee yet expect Iudah and Iſraels vnion in the Empire of the Rabbines? And muſt the Heifer fall againe at Ieruſalem vnder the ſtroke and folly of the Prieſt? This were not to offer a ſacrifice for ſinne; but to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4371:15"/> make the ſacrifice a ſinne: this were not to hope for vnion, and dominion, but to faine them; this were not to fulfill a propheſie, but violate it; and by an impious courteſie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a Prophet, and wrong the Lord of the Prophet. Our Meſſias is come, and hath excuſed the beaſt from ſacrifice, as hee hath excuſed vs from the neceſſitie of ſuch ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Our Meſſias is come, but his Kingdome is not come; his Kingdome being not of this world: though in this world hee did the acts of a King; in vniting Nations, in ſauing Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But did he vnite Iudah and Iſrael, who were ſo diuided that they could onely be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited by that God from whom they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided? Or muſt we with the tedious Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary wait for their vnion, till our ſoules with expectation haue wearied our bodies? Nay, till our ſoules haue left our bodies? Nay, till our ſoules reſume our bodies by our owne vnion at the Reſurrection? And muſt we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that then, when all the world riſes from the graue, it muſt yet but walke in its ſleepe for a thouſand yeeres? And that the Iewes ſhall ſee Chriſt in Ieruſalem, and yet not crucifie him? And that they ſhall haue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4371:16"/> ſuch delights in marriage, that Cerinthus himſelfe, who inuented them, ſhall bee wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them? Alas, at the Reſurrection, there ſhall be no marriage, but of the Lambe; there ſhall be no Ieruſalem, but the heauenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, for Iudah and Iſrael to be vnited in. But will not God in this world vnite them, as in this world he hath promiſed to vnite them? Iudah hath had the bleſſing to returne; and hath not God a bleſſing for Iſrael alſo? hath he not promiſed this bleſſing to Iſrael alſo? Or will not God performe his promiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Iſrael hath not performed the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his promiſe? Indeed hee did not giue them all the land of promiſe; but made ſome of it, alwayes a land but of promiſe; not that he neglected his promiſe made to Them but to make them remember they had neglected their promiſe made to Him; and that they did more prouoke his juſtice, then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then did euer prouoke their paſſion. But now wil you ſee how God doth at once mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his Prophet &amp; his mercy? Will you ſee the progreſſe of his jealouſie, which proues his word to be himſelfe imparted to the eare? Obſerue then the parts of time, by which the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4371:16"/> parts of his promiſe are famouſly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; in which the parts of his promiſe are famouſly juſtified. When Cyrus gaue leaue to the Iewes to depart, not from his Countries, yet to their owne, did hee ſtay Iſrael from this departure? Or did Iſrael ſtay it ſelfe from this departure? Is any man ſo ſtupid, to ſuppoſe Iſrael ſo ſtupid? Doth hee not deſerue captiuitie, that can thinke they would chooſe capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie? Perhaps ſome few (beſides the aged) made their lazie wiſhes trauell to Ieruſalem, in ſteed of themſelues: ſome few, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate ſoules made them captiue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoere they were, although the Aſſyrian had neuer conquered them, and although Cyrus did releaſe them: ſome few, who belike had liued as much without a God, as without a Temple. But Iſrael did returne; the people of Iſrael, though not the name. Iſrael had before left out Gods Name; and now God leaues out theirs; now all is Iudah, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as good, as all. God made them into one name, as well as into one Nation; and to ſhew his loue, gaue them for their Prince a Prince, whom he loued, his ſeruant Dauid; Dauid, not in perſon, but in ſucceſſion. He
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4371:17"/> gaue them Zorobabel, the reſtorer: with whom they returned to their owne land, and were as welcome as the ſpring; with whom they returned to their Ieruſalem, which was as glad of them, as it was once of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; with whome they returned, not to the Temple, yet for the Temple. And thus you ſee them vnited in peace, which is their vnion among themſelues: but now you ſhall ſee them vnited in holineſſe, which is an vnion in themſelues; which is Gods vnion with them. When the Redeemer of Iſrael deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Iſrael, when God vouchſafed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure fleſh, that man might bee as neere Gods nature, as God was pleaſed to be neere mans conuerſation, hee made no difference betweene the Ieruſalem-Iew and the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan-Iew; but prouided Baptiſme to bee ſo tempered for them both, that though they both came vnto it, diuided by an inequalitie of ſinne, they both depart vnited by an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of cleanneſſe. One vnion more you ſhall behold; you ſhall behold it, for as yet you cannot; and this is their vnion in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. You ſaw, before, Gods vnion with them; and this ſhall be their vnion with God; their vnion as new, as the Ieruſalem in which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4371:17"/> it ſhall bee; where Gods ſeruant Dauid ſhall be their King, as long as the new Ieruſalem ſhall bee a Kingdome. Zorobabel had not ſtrength enough to fulfill this promiſe; and our Meſſias had not time enough to fulfill this promiſe: but when time ſhall bee no more, then ſhall our Meſſias the eternall Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid be their King and reſtorer for euermore. And though this their vnion in triump his not yet performed, and their vnion in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but in part performed; yet both ſhall bee, and bee as much their wonder as their happineſſe. But their vnion in peace we haue beheld; and their vnion in peace they alſo might behold; a peace almoſt as admirable, as the Peacemaker. Cyrus and Zorobabel were inſtruments, but God was the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. As at the rayſing of the dead, the bones ſhall returne into their method; and the duſt ſhall bee moulded into fleſh, and the ſinew ſhall gird them into a body, which the breath of the Almighty will inſtruct with a ſoule, a ſoule that ſhall vnderſtand the mercy of the Miracle: ſo was the Reſurrection of Iudah and Iſrael from the graue of Aſſyria. As when a man takes two ſtickes, and joynes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4371:18"/> them one to another into one ſticke, and they become one in his hand, as verely one, as his hand, and more vnited, then the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the hand: So was the vnion of Iudah and Iſrael, ſo plaine, ſo firme in the hand of the almighty. And the almighty did ſtretch out his hand to ſtretch-out this vnion for an example: the fame whereof ſhall laſt, as long as the world, and the bleſſing of it out-laſt the world. The diuiſion of Iudah and Iſrael was the worke of men; which it confeſſed by being bad and ſhort: but the vnion of Iudah and Iſrael was the worke of God, begun on earth, but to bee finiſhed in Heauen; as if it would imitate the Eternitie of the author. It is the art of Gods mercy to vnite ſinners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, and yet by vniting them, not to increaſe their ſinnes; nay, by vniting them, to make their ſinnes the leſſe: but it is the holineſſe of his mercy to vnite ſinners to himſelfe, and by vniting them to make them like himſelfe. This is the bleſſing of Iudah and Iſraels vnion: this is the wonder of the God of vnion! But is there no vnion, which by ſimilitude can be vnited with this vnion? Doth the Creatour of the world confine his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4371:18"/> power to one Country, becauſe hee doth il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate it in one Country? Doth he not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence his wonders like his eſſence, which can be as eminently euery where, as it is truely euerywhere? Could not he make euery won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the world, as broad as the flood, which was a wonder as broad as the world? or could he not as eaſily haue made another floud, as a Rain-bow, by which he tels vs, he will make nere another? And yet if we will view, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, our owne Countrie, we ſhall almoſt aſmuch deceiue our eye, as employ it; whiles we may thinke that as before wee ſaw Iudah and Iſrael carried into Aſſyria, ſo now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a captiuity they are brought into Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or by a Nationall Metempſychoſis, which Pythagoras neuer thought-on, that they are changed into Britanie. Were not both our Britanies ſince the beginning of nature, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by nature? Did not nature prouide one friendly Tweed to purifie the inhabitants of them both, with the ſame waues? Did it not prouide one liberall Cheuiot to aduance them to an equall height of the ſame ſports and proſpect? Behold the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Britanies, ſince they were viſible in earneſt, ſince by exactneſſe of Commerce
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4371:19"/> they haue refined themſelues from fable and neglect, and you ſhall ſee, that they were ſo wonderfully vnited, that there could bee no greater wonder, but that they ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bee diuided. You may ſee how they were vnited in Entertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the Pleaſure of friendſhip, when one King was receiued by another King into his Court and boſome, and yet was neerer to his loue, then to his heart. You may ſee how they were vnited in Marriage, the Conſtancy of friendſhip; when one King would not onely be the neighbour but alſo the Sonne of the other King, &amp; make a neerer vnion then by nature, without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. You may ſee how they were vnited in Warre, the Courage of friendſhip; when one King was not onely ready to liue with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but alſo to die with him; as if they had thought they had not ſufficiently proued their friendſhip, till they had ended it. And at laſt indeed they did end it, and by a quicker way, before death, though ſeldome without it. And you may ſee them proſecute their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion with ſuch degrees of fury; that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention could not more eaſily make you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it were naturall, then the variety make you beleeue it were artificial. Sometime you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4371:19"/> may ſee their paſſion ſo out-runne their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that it runnes out of their Country, and begins a friendſhip with a ſtranger, that it may continue a quarrell with a neighbour; increaſing its ſtrength to increaſe its hatred; and labouring by multitude to bee ſo ſure of reuenge, that it may more juſtly feare its aid, then its enemy. Somtime you may ſee their paſſion ſo impotent, that they will not giue themſelues the reſpite to ſtay for helpe; but preferring a quicke reuenge before a great, make ſmall incurſions for as ſmall ſpoyle; as if many of them were to make vp but one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge; and yet all of them but expreſſe, how they rather wiſhed one another a miſchiefe, then did one. Sometime you ſhall ſee them more vnhappily deliberate, ſetling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in vengeance and a ſiege; ſhutting vp a City, that it may be opened to them; way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon a City, and hating it; vexing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as much with the delay of their deſire, as they could be delighted with the effect of their deſire, and continually more afraid of a repulſe, then the beſieged were of death, nay, then of famine; which had it bin in the beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers trenches, might peraduenture haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken through the wals, and made them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4371:20"/> to make their victory inuiſible, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their enemies their conqueſt, and their food. Sometime you ſhall ſee the bloud of their ſlaine couer their earth; which by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing vſe of the ſlaughter, doth at the fouleneſſe of the fact, bluſh with the ſame bloud, with which it is ſtained; nay, bluſh at the ſlaine, with their owne bloud. You ſhall heare an out-cry for the captiuity of a King; as if it endeavour'd to call him backe againe. You ſhall heare the Trumpet ſound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, for the ſlaughter of a King, though his owne bloud had a lowder voice. And yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold no Aſſyrian to imitate and chaſtize theſe ſlaughters; And yet no deportation of theſe people into ſome land, on which they would haue bin taught to commit no violence, but with the plough. But God did not ſtretch out his hand to judgement; but did correct them with their owne hands, making their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which was their guilt, their puniſhment. He threatned them with captiuity: but gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly did but threaten them. But hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd them both; he conquered them with his mercy; which vndertooke their vnion, when hope and reaſon had forſaken it. Could any man expect they ſhould bee vnited by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4371:20"/> marriage, which was a meanes that in former times had beene prooued to bee weake; and now ſeemed as deſperate, as the warre that followed it; wherein the royall Bridegroome falling by the irreuerent fury of the ſword left an infant for his ſucceſſour, not able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the bleſſing of a Kingdome, or the loſſe of a father; but left a man for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, our laſt Henry, a King full of triumphs and heires? Yet were they vnited from the bleſſing of marriage; and thus their firſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was the vnion of their bodies. Could any man expect they ſhould bee vnited by Religion, whiles they beheld two glorious Queenes, the one famous for wiſdome, the other for wiſdome and happineſſe, the one of age to bring vp her heire, the other of age to beare an heire, but Princes as much diuided by Religion, as they were vnited by nature? Yet were they vnited in their ſucceſſour, who was heire in Royalty to the one, and in Royalty and Religion to the other. Thus were our Britanies vnited from the bleſſing of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage by Religion alſo; and this was the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſoules. And now you will expect they ſhould be vnited in obedience, and now they were vnited in obedience; which was the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4371:21"/> vnion of their perſons: which was the vnion of their bodies and ſoules. And they were ſo obedient to this ſucceſſor, that aſſoon as they heard of him, they did obey him; without ambition, commending their owne obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as much for the expedition, as for the ſinceritie. As ſoone as they heard of him, they did obey him; loyally commanding their King to loue them, by obeying the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of him, which did preuent his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. The report had no ſooner entred the eare, but like the ſoule, it ſtraight informed the whole ſubject. It was in an inſtant in the heart, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding loue: it was in the tongue, commanding acknowledgement; it was in the knee, commmanding worſhip; it was in the hand commanding applauſe; it was in the eye commanding deſire; it was in the foot commanding ſpeed. And yet, as if that had beene too ſlow, the report of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſtriued to be ſwifter then the report of the King, and taking horſe it carried the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger waking and ſleeping. It allowed him ſleepe, but not reſt; as if it would haue proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that euen the ſleepe of a good ſubject is buſie in the Kings ſeruice. But wee haue heard of ſome Kings abroad, that haue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4371:21"/> beene heard-of, yet not ſo ſoone obeyed. When the right Reuerend father in God, Henry King of Portugall had by the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death left his Crowne, as for a Crowne, he had before by the temptation of his right, put off his Cardinals cap, Portugall quickly heard of Philip of Spaine; but did it as quickly obey him? And yet hee was heire to Charles the fift's glory and wiſdome; and yet hee was faine to vſe more wiſdome, by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more force, ere hee could winne obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and ſo whiles diuers Pretenders labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to prooue themſelues to bee neerer the Crowne, hee by a wiſer ſpeed proou'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be neerer the Kingdome. Our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours quickly heard of their greateſt Henry, immortall for all Rauillac's Knife; but did they as quickly obey him? Was hee not faine to make them heare his Drumme, as well as his fame? But when our Peacemaker was heard of, there was no tumult, but of our joy; there was no voice of a Trumpet, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime our joy; there was no lifting vp of a hand, but of the hand that anointed him. God did preuent him with liberall bleſſings; he changed his Cradle into a Throne, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4371:22"/> as ſoone compaſſed his head with a Crowne, as his body with a Swath. His hand did afterward lead him; his hand did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward protect him: and by a new Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doubled his Royalty with his age. God did preuent him with liberall bleſſings: God did preuent vs with liberall bleſſings. He bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs with a vnion as quiet as ſleepe or a good conſcience. We haue heard of ſome v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in our owne Country: and it is a chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſorrow to haue heard of them, then to haue ſeene them: ſince they were as much attended with bloud, as with victory. The old Saxons were vnited, but it was by ruine; nay, it was into ruine; they did rather fall into vnion, then riſe by it; and their bloud ſeemes ſtill as freſh as their ſtory. Our eldeſt Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, who lay diuided from the Saxons by injury and melancholy, could not yet lie hid from the inquiſitiue ſword of our firſt Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; which forced them all to vnion, either in death or obedience; though at laſt they were fully vnited, and recompenſed for all their afflictions in our wiſeſt Henrie, in their Henrie; in whom their bloud was repair'd and honour'd. The two Royall Houſes of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4371:22"/> Yorke and Lancaſter were at laſt vnited, yet not without diuiſion; and they were faine to ſhed ſome bloud, that they might ſhed no more bloud. The Vſurper, that great Artiſt, muſt become as foule in his death, as in his plots, and loſe his bloud, ere Henry and Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth by the holy vnion of marriage could mixe theirs. But God did preuent vs with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall bleſſings; hee did with peace, preuent our peace, and alſo made for vs a greater bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, then peace, the continuance of it. When our enemies opened their mouthes to reuile vs, when they opened their mouthes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure vs; when they ſaid, God hath diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured them to the protection of a Woman; nay, when they ſaid, they ſhall loſe euen that protection, though not that diſhonour; when they had meaſured our iniquity (for their owne indeed could not bee meaſured) and had made-vp God Almighties accounts for him without his notice: then did the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty aduance himſelfe in his jealouſie, and in his people: then did hee aduance the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as before, the victory of that Queene, which perpetually conquered her enemies, and her ſexe; then did he aduance the pietie
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4371:23"/> of our King, as the King had encreaſed it. He placed him before in the kingdom of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, but now in the Throne; and made him as well acquainted with the Chaire, as with the Propheſie; then did he aduance our peace like our peacemaker. O happy Britanies vnited in the ſame juſtice, though not in the ſame lawes, which differ more in their forme, then in their purpoſe. O happy Britanies v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in the ſame honours, in the ſame ſignes of honour; the glorious wreath of our white and red Roſes, which was before vnited but with an Embleme, a knot, being now vnited ſurer without a knot, being now defended ſurer from any irreuerent touch by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of the Thiſtle. The Roſe hath natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a little of the Thiſtle; but ours haue the whole Thiſtle; they had before the ſharpneſſe of it, but now the company. O happy Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies vnited now in the diſcipline of Religion, as before in Religion; Now doe wee all not onely ſerue the ſame God in the ſame truth, but alſo in the ſame manner: and the Prieſts of God are ſo farre from being diuided in opinion, that they are vnited euen in apparel, which, as wel as the body, is taught an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4371:23"/> to the ſame Commandement. A Prelate and an Organ are now no newes; but the one is euery where more ſacred then a father; the other as cheerfull as a Pſalme. And in the voice of a Pſalme will we prayſe thee, O thou God of Pſalmes; and in the cunning and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined breath of an Organ, will wee imitate and praiſe thee, O thou Creatour of our breath, that haſt giuen vs another breath, our King, the breath of our noſtrils. And by thy bleſſing, in thy bleſſing, in our peace, will we prayſe thee, O thou Prince of peace! Thou, that makeſt the Wolfe dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard lye downe with the Kid: and the Calfe, and the young Lion, and the Fatling together, and a little Child to lead them; thou that makeſt the Cow and the Beare feed, and their young ones lye downe together: and the Lion eat ſtraw, like the Oxe; thou that makeſt the ſucking child play on the hole of the Aſpe, and the weaned child put his hand on the Cockatrice denne! in our peace will we prayſe thee, O thou Prince of peace; that haſt broken downe our partition wall; which now was no more able to hinder our peace, then it was before
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4371:24"/> able to procure it. And as thou haſt thus made way for vs to meete together to enjoy this bleſſing of our vnion: ſo by this bleſſing haue we now made vſe of that way, and met together to acknowledge this bleſſing of our vnion. And here with vnion of heart and voice we render vnited prayſes vnto thee, O thou God of vnion! Who haſt this day crowned thy King with fauour, who haſt this day crowned thy ſelfe with glory; whiles this day thou haſt crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thy people with a King.</p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:26"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4371:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4371:30"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4371:30"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4371:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:4371:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4371:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4371:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4371:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:4371:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4371:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4371:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
